Guide to the Records of WNYU (Radio Station: New York, N.Y.) RG.39.5
New York University Archives
Records of WNYU
1949-1985
New York University Archives
WNYU (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
RG.39.5
4.5 Linear Feet in 9 boxes
WNYU was formed in 1949 on the University Heights campus of New York University by a group of engineers. The records of WNYU Radio Station were transferred to the New York University Archives when the radio station was moved from Gould Memorial Library at the University Heights campus to Loeb Student Center on Washington Square in June 1973. The records cover the years 1949-1969 and deal with the activities of WNYU radio station and the efforts and persistence of WNYU's staff to build up an AM-FM radio station and maintain its broadcasting as one of the best educational radio stations in the New York metropolitan area. The collection is predominantly composed of correspondence between WNYU's staff and other constituent parts of the University. Other correspondence relates to the broader media and metropolitan community.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged chronologically; series II is arranged alphabetically by subject; and series III is arranged alphabetically by type of material. Series V has not been arranged by an archivist.
This collection has been organized into five series:
Series:
Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda
Drawings
Publications
Subject Files
2015 Accretion
Scope and Contents
The records include correspondence of Joseph Steinberg, the station's manager during the 1960s with University offices; the Inter-Colligiate Broadcasting System; and Miller, Montgomery & Spanding concerning construction for WNYU facilities. There also exists within the collection correspondence of Larry J. Hollander, the faculty advisor to the WYNU staff, with Steinberg; correspondence of the staff with fellow radio stations including the Columbia University station, concerning such topics as the election of 1964, Ray Nelson, and a Senator Claiborne Pell interview about youth legislation; letters from The New York Times to Arnold Rosner, Director of Classical Music at WNYU; letters from the Police Department of New York City; and letters from United Press International. Also included are minutes of meetings of the WNYU Board of Directors, budget reports and operating expense estimates of WNYU members, log forms, schedules, applications, architectural drawings, certificates from Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company, advertising brochures, programs, newsletters, and printed promotional material.
History of WNYU
WNYU was formed in 1949 on the University Heights campus of New York University by a group of engineers. Initially, the station only broadcast to the University Heights cafeteria. Well established by 1956, WNYU became a member of the Inter-Collegiate Broadcasting System (IBS). In 1955 the radio division of the Television, Motion Picture and Radio Department of the Communications Arts Group started a closed circuit station, WCAG, at the Washington Square Campus. In 1963 WNYU (Heights Station) and WCAG (Washington Square Station) merged into one closed circuit radio station through the use of a telephone cable. It was decided that WCAG would broadcast to both campuses during the day while WNYU would take over in the evenings. This continued until 1973, when NYU sold the University Heights campus. At that time the equipment was brought to Loeb Student Center on Washington Square. During the period of 1965-1973 the station worked to acquire an FM frequency. In 1965 NYU made an agreement with the United Nations to use their channel, "206." NYU submitted their first application to the Federal Communication Commission (FCC) in 1965. After three years the FCC decided that channel "206" should be shared by NYU and Fairleigh Dickinson University of New Jersey. WNYU broadcast from 4 p.m. to 1 a.m. on weekdays.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. This collection contains audiovisual materials that have not been digitized. Please contact the University Archives if you wish to access these materials.
Custodial History
The records of WNYU Radio Station were transferred to the New York University Archives when the radio station was moved from Gould Memorial Library at the University Heights campus to Loeb Student Center on Washington Square in June 1973. Further accretions to the collection have been added in the intervening years.
Architectural drawings (visual works); Job applications.; Newsletters.; Minutes (administrative records); Petitions.; Radio in education.; Advertisements.; Radio broadcasting |x Rules and regulations.; Radio broadcasting |x Management.; Radio broadcasting -- History; Radio broadcasting |v Archival resources.; Radio |x Equipment and supplies.; Hollander, Larry J.; Fairleigh Dickinson University -- Radio broadcasting; Columbia University -- Radio broadcasting; Nelson, Ray; Miller, Montgomery & Spanding; Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company; Inter-Collegiate Broadcasting System; New York University -- Radio broadcasting; New York University. Communication Arts Group; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; New York Times Company; Steinberg, Joseph; United Nations; Pell, Claiborne, 1918-2009; Rosner, Arnold, 1945-; WNYU (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); United Press International; WCAG (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda: 1949-1969.
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 29, 1949 -April 8, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Feb. 17, 1955 -Dec. 27, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 28, 1956 -May 7, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Dec. 9, 1957 -Sept. 23, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 5, 1958 -Mar. 18, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 29, 1960 -Nov. 15, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Oral history interview by Blair Schomaker, Undated; Schomaker, Blair (Box 1, Folder 7, Cassette 1)
      Scope and contents
      This recording contains an interview with an unnamed male, made for the NYU Archives, about the history and establishment of WNYU.
      Original format
      90-minute Memorex audio cassette
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 20, 1960 -Feb. 27, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 8, 1962 -Nov. 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Mar. 1, 1963 -Dec. 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Mar. 1, 1963 -Dec. 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 3, 1963 -May 14, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Oct. 7, 1963 -Dec. 6, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Aug. 10, 1964-May 25, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Oct. 11, 1964 -May 12, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 5, 1964 -Mar. 11, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Dec. 14, 1964 -Apr. 18, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Feb. 21, 1964 -Jun. 15, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 12, 1965 -Dec. 18, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 29, 1965 -Sept. 22, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Aug. 31, 1965 -May 16, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Oct. 14, 1965 -Oct. 19, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 18, 1965 -Apr. 19, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Radio Station WFDU, 1965 -1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Convention, 1965 -1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 17, 1966-Aug. 15, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Feb. 21, 1966 -Oct. 31, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 22, 1966 -Apr. 18, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 17, 1967 -Dec. 4, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 6, 1967 -Jun. 6, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jun. 17, 1968 -Dec. 20, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 6, 1969 -Feb. 6, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - WNYU log forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series II: Drawings
  - Drawings of WNYU radio station, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Drawings of WNYU radio station, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Publications
  - Newspapers, Feb. 1967 -May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, Jan. 1957 -Oct. 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 1967-1981
  - Advisors, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Arbitron, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - (FCC) Docket No. 17454 File No. BPED-742, Docket No. 17455 File No. BPED-751 - Vol. I, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - (FCC) Docket No. 17454 File No. BPED-742, Docket No. 17455 File No. BPED-751 - Vol. II (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - (FCC) Docket No. 17454 File No. BPED-742, Docket No. 17455 File No. BPED-751 - Reply, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Engineering, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - FCC Permit & License Copies, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Fundraising, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Graduates: Personnel Questionnaires, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Inactive Personnel, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Legal- Wilner & Scheiner, 1971-1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Legal-FCC agreement with FDU, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Maggin, Jane (Director of Student Affairs, WNYU Advisor), 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Management Committee Meeting Minutes, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Management & Staff Meetings, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - News Stylebook, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Operations, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Policy (By Laws)- Folder 1 of 2, 1967-1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Policy (By Laws)- Folder 2 of 2, 1967-1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Press, 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases, 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Program Highlights, 1974-1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Program Highlights, 1974-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Program Material, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Programming- Folder 1 of 2, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Programming- Folder 2 of 2, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Programming, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Programming, 1977-1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Publicity & Promotion- Folder 1 of 2, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Publicity & Promotion- Folder 2 of 2, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Reports, Agenda, Staff Questionnaires, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Share-Time Agreement WFDU/WNYU, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Staff Questionnaire, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - STL (Studio-Transmitter Link), 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ultra-Violet, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 9)